<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Publications on Thomas de Graaff</title>
    <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Publications on Thomas de Graaff</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 10 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>On the estimation of spatial stochastic frontier models. An alternative skew-normal approach</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/spatialfrontier/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/spatialfrontier/</guid>
      <description>This paper deals with an alternative approach to combine spatial dependence and stochastic frontier models using a large statistical literature on skew-normal distribution functions. I show how to combine a spatial dependence structure with a stochastic frontier model, that is, (1) straightforward to estimate, (2) able to combine spatial dependence and a technical efficiency term in a single error term, and (3) produce consistent estimates. With smaller sample sizes estimation of the parameter, governing technical efficiencies becomes imprecise.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Does new information technology change commuting behavior?</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/information-technology/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/information-technology/</guid>
      <description>We estimate the long-run causal effect of information technology, i.e., Internet and powerful computers, as measured by the adoption of teleworking, on average commuting distance within professions in the Netherlands. We employ data for 2 years, 1996 when information technology was hardly adopted and 2010 when information technology was widely used in a wide range of professions. Variation in information technology adoption over time and between professions allows us to infer the causal effect of interest using difference-in-differences techniques combined with propensity score matching.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Urban regions as engines of economic growth</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/urbanregions/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/urbanregions/</guid>
      <description>summary In new regional economic policies, national and regional agendas are aligned and reinforce each other. The agendas are based on a joint strategy that combines policy areas; policies aimed at strengthening the economic structure also encompass plans of action for human capital, the residential environment, the physical environment and infrastructures.
Government authorities can make a difference to regional economic growth. In economically successful regions, government authorities play an active role by facilitating growth processes and investing in them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Valuation of Ethnic Diversity. Heterogeneous Effects in an Integrated Labor and Housing Market</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/valuationofethnicdiveristy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/valuationofethnicdiveristy/</guid>
      <description>We estimate the heterogeneous impact of the scale, composition and consumer good-effect of ethnic diversity on individuals&amp;rsquo; job and residential location. Using an extensive pooled micro panel-data set in which homeowners in the Netherlands are identified in both the housing and labor market we can derive the combined effect of ethnic diversity in both markets. We test a model that integrates the utility and production function such that the location of work and residence are determined simultaneously by taking into account observed and unobserved heterogeneous individual behavior on both markets.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Varying Youth Cohort Effects on Regional Labour Market Outcomes in Germany</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/youthcohorteffects/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/youthcohorteffects/</guid>
      <description>We assess how changes in youth cohort sizes effect employment rates in German labour market regions. Replicating the conventional approach, we estimate that a percentage increase in the youth share reduces regional employment rates by −0.2%. We challenge the assumption that cohort size effects are homogenous across space and find robust evidence that the negative effect of youth cohort size is more pronounced in the labour markets of metropolitan regions. These results suggest an upward pressure on urban regional employment rates as a result of the projected decrease in the size of the German youth share.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Barriers of Culture, Networks, and Language in International Migration. A Review</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/barriersofculture/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/barriersofculture/</guid>
      <description>Along with the increasing pace of globalization, recent decades faced a dramatically increase in international migrant flows as well. Compared to the flows of trade, capital and knowledge, we observe that contemporaneous complex institutional differences, historical backgrounds, and individuals&amp;rsquo; diverse socio-demographic characteristics make the migrant workers&amp;rsquo; choice of destination arguably much more uncontrollable. This study shows that migration is in a complex way intertwined with culture, networks and language, (i) by reviewing related studies on the barriers of culture, networks and language in international labor mobility, and (ii) by exploring missing gaps and prospective avenues for research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social Interactions and Crime Revisited. An Investigation Using Individual Offender Rates</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/socialinteractions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/socialinteractions/</guid>
      <description>Using data on the age, sex, ethnicity, and criminal involvement of more than 14 million residents of all ages residing in approximately 4,000 Dutch neighborhoods, we test if an individual&#39;s criminal involvement is affected by the proportion of criminals living in his or her residential neighborhood. We develop a binomial discrete choice model for criminal involvement and estimate it on individual data. We control for both the endogeneity that may be related to unobserved neighborhood characteristics and for sorting behavior.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stedelijke regio&#39;s als motoren van economische groei. Wat kan beleid doen?</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/stedelijkeregios/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/stedelijkeregios/</guid>
      <description>Bevindingen Nederland heeft behoefte aan nieuw regionaaleconomisch beleid. Een beleid waarin nationale en regionale agenda’s op elkaar zijn afgestemd en elkaar versterken. Deze agenda’s zijn gebaseerd op een gezamenlijke strategie waarin beleidsdomeinen worden gecombineerd: beleid gericht op het versterken van de economische structuur bestaat óók uit beleid gericht op menselijk kapitaal, woon- en leefomgevingsbeleid, en fysiek (infrastructureel) beleid.
Overheden kunnen het verschil maken voor regionaal-economische groei. In economisch succesvolle regio’s spelen overheden een actieve rol: zij faciliteren groeiprocessen en investeren daarin.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Look Who&#39;s Talking. On the Heterogeneous Returns to Foreign Language Use at Work among Natives and Migrants in Europe</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/lookwhoistalking/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/lookwhoistalking/</guid>
      <description>We examine the heterogeneous impacts of foreign language use at work on earnings of both native-born workers and foreign-born workers, using a longitudinal survey, viz. the European Community Household Panel (ECHP) running from 1994 to 2001. Our findings are the following. First, for native-born workers with a tertiary diploma, using a foreign language at work is found to have an unambiguously positive impact on their earnings (2% on average). Second, for foreign-born workers, returns to foreign language use at work is highly complementary to education.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Does new information technology change commuting behavior</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/newinformationtechnology/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/newinformationtechnology/</guid>
      <description>We estimate the long-run causal effect of information technology, i.e. Internet and powerful computers, on average commuting distance within professions in the Netherlands. We employ data for two years—1996 when information technology was hardly adopted and 2010 when information technology was widely used in a wide range of professions. Variation in information technology adoption over time and between professions allows us to infer the causal effect of interest using difference-in-differences techniques combined with propensity score matching.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Looking at John Snow’s Cholera Map from the Twenty First Century. A Practical Primer on Reproducibility and Open Science</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/john-snow/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/john-snow/</guid>
      <description>This chapter (This manuscript is a chapter version of the original document, which is a reproducible online notebook. The entire, version-controlled project can be found online at: https://bitbucket.org/darribas/reproducible_john_snow.) presents an entirely reproducible spatial analysis of the classic John Snow’s map of the 1854 cholera epidemic in London. The analysis draws on many of the techniques most commonly used by regional scientists, such as choropleth mapping, spatial autocorrelation, and point pattern analysis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Demographic Aging and Employment Dynamics in German Regions. Modeling Regional Heterogeneity</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/2017-05-01-demographic-ageing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/2017-05-01-demographic-ageing/</guid>
      <description>Persistence of high youth unemployment and dismal labour market outcomes are imminent concerns for most European economies. The relationship between demographic ageing and employment outcomes is even more worrying once the relationship is scrutinized at the regional level. We focus on modelling regional heterogeneity. We argue that an average impact across regions is often not very useful, and that – conditional on the region&#39;s characteristics – impacts may differ significantly.We advocate the use of modelling varying level and slope effects, and specifically to cluster them by the use of latent class or finite mixture models (FMMs).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Competitive network positions in trade and structural economic growth. A geographically weighted regression analysis for European regions</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/competitivenetworkpositions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/competitivenetworkpositions/</guid>
      <description>In this paper, we introduce network dependence in European regional growth analy- ses in two new ways. First, we use detailed trade-flow data across European regions to decom- pose regional economic growth into two components: demand-led growth due to growing export markets and structural growth due to growing market shares in those export markets. Only structural growth, constituting on average approximately 20 per cent of total growth, is po- tentially affected by regionally varying locational characteristics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cultural Diversity and Cultural Distance as Choice Determinants of Migration Destination</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/culturaldiversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/culturaldiversity/</guid>
      <description>This study analyses the impact of cultural composition on regional attractiveness from the perspective of international migrant sorting behaviour on a European regional NUTS1 level. We use an attitudinal survey to quantify cultural distances between natives and immigrants in the region concerned, and estimate the migrants’ varying preferences for both cultural diversity and cultural distance. To account for regional unobserved heterogeneity, our econometric analysis employs artificial instrumental variables, as developed by Bayer et al.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>WooW-II. Workshop on open workflows</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/woowii/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/woowii/</guid>
      <description>This resource describes WooW-II, a two-day workshop on open workflows for quantitative social scientists. The workshop is broken down in five main parts, where each of them typically consists of an introductionary tutorial and a hands-on assignment. The specific tools discussed in this workshop are Markdown, Pandoc, Git, Github, R, and Rstudio, but the theoretical approach applies to a wider range of tools (e.g., LATEX and Python). By the end of the workshop, participants should be able to reproduce a paper of their own and make it available in an open form applying the concepts and tools introduced.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Product Heterogeneity, Intangible Barriers and Distance Decay. The Effect of Multiple Dimensions of Distance on Trade across Different Product Categories</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/productheterogeneity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/productheterogeneity/</guid>
      <description>We empirically examine the heterogeneity in the effects of multiple dimensions of distance on trade across detailed product groups. Using finite mixture modelling on bilateral trade data at the three-digit Standard International Trade Classification level, we endogenously group product categories into an a priori unknown number of segments based on estimated coefficients of multiple dimensions of distance in the gravity equation. We find that institutional distance, belonging to the same trade bloc and especially geographical distance are crucial and distinct factors for classifying commodities into homogeneous product groups.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sorting out the impact of cultural diversity on innovative firms. An empirical analysis of Dutch micro-data</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/innovative-firms/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/innovative-firms/</guid>
      <description>An increasing amount of research in the migration literature shows a positive association between migrant diversity and firm productivity. However, the potential bias due to unobserved heterogeneity remains a challenge. In this paper we analyse the impact of cultural diversity on firm innovativeness, while using finite mixture modeling to control for observed and unobserved heterogeneity. Recent availability of microdata has enabled us to construct a linked employee-employer dataset through merging datasets on both workers and firms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Living and working in ethnic enclaves. English Language proficiency of immigrants in US metropolitan areas</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/living-and-working-in-ethnic-enclaves/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/living-and-working-in-ethnic-enclaves/</guid>
      <description>We use data on Mexican and Chinese immigrants in the US to calculate the average marginal effects of residential and occupational segregation on immigrants&amp;rsquo; ability to speak English, and similarly the effects of English fluency of family members. Our results confirm that residential segregation is generally inversely related to English language proficiency of immigrants, except for skilled Chinese immigrants. Allowing for occupational fixed effects, the minority population share at the place of work is relevant for proficiency in English among skilled Chinese, but not for Mexicans and unskilled Chinese.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A European Cross-Country Comparison of the Impact of Homeownership and Transaction Costs on Job Tenure</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/european-crosscountry-comparison/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/european-crosscountry-comparison/</guid>
      <description>A European cross-country comparison of the impact of homeownership and transaction costs on job tenure, Regional Studies. This paper looks at the impacts across European countries of homeownership and transaction costs on job tenure. The analysis is based on a representative household sample of fourteen European countries covering the period 1994–2001. These data are merged with country-specific transaction tax data and aggregate homeownership rates. Similar to previous microeconomic studies, the results indicate that homeownership reduces job mobility as well as the probability of becoming unemployed or economically inactive.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Population-Employment Interaction Model as Labour Module in TIGRIS XL</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/population-employment/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/population-employment/</guid>
      <description>This chapter looks at the integration of a population-employment interaction model in the TIGRIS XL framework. TIGRIS XL model is an integrated land-use and transport model and is actually a system of sub-models (or modules) that allows for dynamic interaction between them. Currently, the population module responses to lagged changes in employment and the employment module responses to contemporaneous changes in population. Thus, the change in population mainly drives the change in employment—an assumption which, given the strict Dutch restrictions on population location, is not entirely unrealistic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sectoral heterogeneity, accessibility and population–employment dynamics in Dutch cities</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/sectoral-heterogeneity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/sectoral-heterogeneity/</guid>
      <description>In the Netherlands, the diminishing accessibility of locations of consumers, producers and services potentially hampers economic growth. Reducing congestion is therefore one of the pivotal challenges for Dutch policymakers. In this paper we analyze population–employment dynamics in the Netherlands and concurrently decompose total employment into four broad sectors: manufacturing, distribution, business service and personal service activities. We explicitly allow for inter-sectoral relations to capture employment dynamics more accurately. We introduce a model in which endogeneity and spatial autocorrelation are dealt with by a generalized spatial three stage least squares (3SLS) estimator.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welfare effects of road pricing and traffic information under alternative ownership regimes</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/welfare-effects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jun 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/welfare-effects/</guid>
      <description>This paper models strategic interactions between a road supplier, a provider of traffic information, and road users, with stochastic travel times. Using a game-theoretical analysis of suppliers’ pricing strategies, we assess the social welfare effects of traffic information under various ownership regimes. The results show that the distortive welfare effect of monopolistic information pricing appears relatively small. Collusion of the road operator and information provider yields higher social welfare than independent pricing by two firms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Regional Population-Employment Dynamics Across Different Sectors of the Economy</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/regional-population-employment-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/regional-population-employment-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>An important subset of the literature on agglomeration externalities hypothesizes that intrasectoral and intersectoral relations are endogenously determined in models of local and regional economic growth. Remarkably, structural adjustment models describing the spatio-temporal dynamics of population and employment levels or growth traditionally do not include intersectoral economic dynamics. This paper argues and shows that allowing for economic linkages across sectors in these models adds considerable value, especially in forecasting. An econometric model of population–employment dynamics, in which sectoral variations in economic development are explicitly taken into account, is applied to a large urban planning policy proposal in the Netherlands.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Socio-economic impacts of migrant clustering on Dutch neighbourhoods. In search of optimal migrant diversity</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/socio-economic-impacts/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/socio-economic-impacts/</guid>
      <description>The recent empirical literature on the impact of migrant clustering on socio-economic welfare indicators shows inconclusive and often even contradictory results. In this paper we argue that there is not an unambiguous empirical outcome of migrant or ethnic diversity, but that it depends on the level of migrant or ethnic composition itself. A low degree of socio-economic and cultural diversity may be beneficial for neighbourhoods, whereas an excessive degree of diversity may be harmful.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The role of human capital in language acquisition among immigrants in US metropolitan</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/the-role-of-human-capital/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/the-role-of-human-capital/</guid>
      <description>Segregation by race, ethnicity and income is a persistent feature of US cities and communities, and ethnic enclaves have formed ever since immigration became more diverse. For low-skilled immigrants in particular, settling in an ethnic enclave may offer important opportunities and facilitate coping with the new environment. However, immigrant enclaves may also foster occupational segregation and retard assimilation, with the willingness to invest in language acquisition playing a key role. This paper expands on earlier work focusing on the linkage between spatial segregation and language acquisition.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Spatial Differences in the Attractiveness of Dutch Museums</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/spatial-differences-museums/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/spatial-differences-museums/</guid>
      <description>Museums may serve as important amenities for inhabitants and act as magnets for attracting visitors to a city. For city planners it is important to understand what different types of museums there are in terms of attraction power, and how their attractiveness may depend on the presence of other museums. To this end, we propose a gravity model for all museums allowing for spatial dependence between museums to account for local competition or synergy effects.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Homeownership, Social Renting, and Labour Mobility across Europe</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/homeownership-socialrenting/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/homeownership-socialrenting/</guid>
      <description>European unemployment is the main focus of this chapter. The chapter looks at various transaction costs such as financial, psychological, social, cultural, religious, and ethnic transaction costs. This chapter describes the differences in residence mobility patterns and social renting institutions in several countries. The chapter asserts that even if social leasing and privately owned residences encourage housing transaction expenditures, only renting heightens a person&#39;s probability of becoming unemployed. Potential justifications would be related to the relative returns of investment as well as the disadvantages perceived by both parties — homeowners and social renters.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Define the Optimal Level of Public-sector Infrastructure Development? A Conceptual Model for Decision-making in Infrastructure Projects</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/optimal-level/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/optimal-level/</guid>
      <description>Debates with respect to financial problems of public-sector infrastructure development increasingly focus on ways to improve value capturing. Two issues play a crucial role in this debate: how much value can be captured and how can we maximize the value to be captured? In this paper a conceptual model is presented that enables defining the optimal level of public sector infrastructure development—combining a social and financial perspective. Using the model, it is possible, in principle, to define the maximum level of value capturing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Woon-werkdynamiek in Nederlandse gemeenten</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/woon-werk-dynameik/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/woon-werk-dynameik/</guid>
      <description>Bevindingen  Het gebrek aan ruimtelijk gedetailleerd inzicht in de woon-werkdynamiek in Nederland vormt een belangrijke handicap in de discussies over de planningsopgave voor wonen en werken en de relatie hiertussen. De vraag of mensen gaan wonen waar de kans op voor hen geschikte banen optimaal is, of andersom – dat bedrijven zich vestigen op plaatsen waar een groot aanbod aan arbeidspotentieel is –, is kaderstellend en richtinggevend voor de planning van woningbouw- en werklocaties in Nederland.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Measuring the WTP for shopping facilities around railway stations</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/measuring-the-wtp/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/measuring-the-wtp/</guid>
      <description>Railway stations often function as a nexus of various activities, such as transport, shopping and working. Larger stations especially act as nodes for several transport modes, including heavy rail, light rail and city bus transport. Therefore, it is precisely due to their strategic and accessible locations that specific railway stations increasingly become more attractive for the location of firms. Because station areas potentially act as magnets for service sector firms (particularly) and in combination with increased traffic density, these areas also attract many smaller facilitative firms, such as shops, childcare centres, and restaurants.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>De Invloed van Bereikbaarheid op Vastgoedwaarden van Kantoren</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/bereikbaarheid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Sep 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/bereikbaarheid/</guid>
      <description>Paper presented at CVS conference in Antwerp, 2009.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The WTP for Facilities at the Amsterdam Zuidas</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/wtp-facilities/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Sep 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/wtp-facilities/</guid>
      <description>This paper reports the results of a stated preference study investigating the willingness-to-pay (WTP) of employees at the Amsterdam Zuidas for the presence of nonshopping and shopping facilities. The Amsterdam Zuidas area, surrounding the current train–metro–tram station Amsterdam Zuid World-Trade-Centre, is the largest multifunctional land-use project currently under development in the Netherlands. For nonshopping facilities, the results show that employees have the highest WTP for the presence of day-care centres and public transport facilities, and the lowest for public and recreation facilities.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Substitution between working at home and out-of-home. The role of ICT and commuting costs</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/substitutionict/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Feb 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/substitutionict/</guid>
      <description>This paper analyzes the trade-off between working at home and out-of-home, ICT and commuting time. To this end, we develop a microeconomic demand system, which explicitly incorporates both time and income constraints. Commuting time is considered as the price to be paid for working out-of-home and a decrease in earnings as the price for working at home. For the latter, we find that working at home leads to a (marginally significant) reduction of the wage rate of about 19%, but this gap largely disappears when ICT is used for at home work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Spatial Economic Perspective on Language Acquisition. Segregation, Networking, and Assimilation of Immigrants</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/a-spatial-economic-perspective/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/a-spatial-economic-perspective/</guid>
      <description>Immigration and multiculturalism are at the heart of modern Western societies. The issue of language acquisition of immigrants is intrinsically linked to immigration. We formally link language acquisition of immigrants to the relative size of the immigrant stock, employing a microeconomic trading framework. Our model allows for spatial interaction going beyond the immigrant&#39;s area of residence, and explicitly incorporates spatial segregation. In addition, behavioral differences of immigrants with respect to their level of assimilation into the host country, as well as differences in networking within their own ethnic community, are accounted for.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the Substitution and Complementarity between Telework and Travel. A Review and Application</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/substitutionandcomplemetarity/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jun 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/substitutionandcomplemetarity/</guid>
      <description>This paper offers a review of the scientific evidence regarding the relation between ICT and travel in general and ICT and commuting in particular. It focuses on the issue of teleworking at home and ignores other interesting phenomena as teleworking centers. The conclusions can be summarized as follows. In the short run, ICT and commuting are to be regarded as weak substitutes, although the relation differs across population groups and parts of the day.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Performance of Diagnostic Tests for Spatial Dependence in Linear Regression Models. A Meta-Analysis of Simulation Studies</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/diagnostictests/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 May 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/diagnostictests/</guid>
      <description>One of the reasons for A.D. Cliff and J.K. Ord’s 1973 book &amp;ldquo;Spatial Autocorrelation&amp;rdquo; achieving the status of a seminal work on spatial statistics and econometrics lies in their careful and lucid treatment of the autocorrelation problem in spatial data series. Cliff and Ord present test statistics for univariate spatial series of categorical (nominal and ordinal) and continuous (interval or ratio scale) data. They extend the use of autocorrelation statistics, specifically Moran’s I (Moran, 1948), to the analysis of regression residuals (see also Cliff and Ord, 1972).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ICT and Substitution Between Out-of-Home and at-Home Work. The Importance of Timing</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/ict-and-substitution/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/ict-and-substitution/</guid>
      <description>This paper investigates the determinants of at-home and out-of-home labor supply in the Netherlands in the 1990s, focusing on the presence of information and computer technology (ICT) in households—in particular modem possession. To investigate these determinants, a sequential hurdle model is estimated in which people first decide to work and then decide to divide total labor supply in at-home and out-of-home labor supply. To correct for possible endogeneity, the modem variable is estimated by means of instrumental variables.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ethnic Concentration and Human Capital Formation</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/ethnic-concentration/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/ethnic-concentration/</guid>
      <description>Concentration of immigrants and its associated externalities have become an important topic in contemporary international migration research, both from a methodological as well as an empirical perspective. The purpose of this chapter is twofold. First, it aims to provide an overview of that part of the migration literature that is concerned with the externalities created by the influx of immigrants. Second, it presents a stylized model in which human capital accumulation and ethnic cluster formation are explicitly incorporated.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resilience. An Evolutionary Approach to Spatial Economic Systems</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/resilience/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2002 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/resilience/</guid>
      <description>The concept of resilience has received a great deal of attention in the past decades. Starting from the first fundamental definitions offered by Holling, Pimms and Perrings in an economic-ecological modeling context, the present paper explores the ‘evolution’ of the resilience concept—as well as related different measures—in both a continuous and discrete time setting.
From this perspective, the paper explores the relevance of the resilience concept in socio-economic systems, by focussing the attention on the relationships among resilience, transition dynamics and lock-in effects, in particular in the light of the dynamics of technological innovation diffusion and adaptive behaviour of firms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Migration, ethnic minorities and network externalities</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/migration/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2002 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/migration/</guid>
      <description>Preface Four years ago, when I explained to my family that I hoped to become a doctor, most people became rather confused and were convinced that I had entered a medical profession. For years, I was asked to look at swollen ankles and bruised knees. Finally, the notion that I was just continuing my studies gradually became apparent to most of them. Not only to family, but to most people the real meaning of writing a Ph.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A General Misspecification Test for Spatial Regression Models. Dependence, Heterogeneity, and Nonlinearity</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/generalmisspeficationtest/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/publications/generalmisspeficationtest/</guid>
      <description>There is an increasing awareness of the potentials of nonlinear modeling in regional science. This can be explained partly by the recognition of the limitations of conventional equilibrium models in complex situations, and also by the easy availability and accessibility of sophisticated computational techniques. Among the class of nonlinear models, dynamic variants based on, for example, chaos theory stand out as an interesting approach. However, the operational significance of such approaches is still rather limited and a rigorous statistical-econometric treatment of nonlinear dynamic modeling experiments is lacking.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>