<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Heterogeneity on Thomas de Graaff</title>
    <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/categories/heterogeneity/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Heterogeneity on Thomas de Graaff</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 18 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="thomasdegraaff.nl/categories/heterogeneity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Valuation of Ethnic Diversity: Heterogeneous Effects in an Integrated Labor and Housing Market</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/2018-11-18-valuationofethnicdiversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/2018-11-18-valuationofethnicdiversity/</guid>
      <description>Our paper Valuation of Ethnic Diversity: Heterogeneous Effects in an Integrated Labor and Housing Market written together with Jessie Bakens is accepted in the Journal of Economic Geopraphy. Jessie and I worked quite hard on this and I am glad that we got the results. The abstract reads as follows:
&amp;gt;We estimate the heterogeneous impact of the scale, composition and consumer good-effect of ethnic diversity on individuals&#39; job and residential location.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sortingmod: an R-package for sorting models</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/sortingmod-an-r-package-for-sorting-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/sortingmod-an-r-package-for-sorting-models/</guid>
      <description>Overview sortingmod is a package for estimating the sorting model - a discrete choice model which explains the location decision of heterogeneous individuals over a set of alternative locations. The model is developed by Bayer et al. (2004) following the work of Berry et al. (1995). It relies on the assumptions that individuals choose a location that maximizes their utility, and that heterogeneous individuals with different characteristics have different preferences, and different valuation for location characteristics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Heatmap of the Robustness of Determinants of European City growth</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/a-heatmap-of-the-robustness-of-determinants-of-european-city-growth/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/a-heatmap-of-the-robustness-of-determinants-of-european-city-growth/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Understanding what makes a city tick (e.g., the determinants that makes cities succesful in employment of economic growth) is vital for both policy makers and (regional) economists. Indeed, local policy makers usually want to know what they can contribute to the performance of their city or region. If policy makers can at all influence the performance, then most likely instruments vary between cities and regions. What is good for one city is not necessarily good for another.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social Interaction and Crime</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/2016-09-12-socialinteractionandcrime/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/2016-09-12-socialinteractionandcrime/</guid>
      <description>Social Interaction and Crime: An Investigation Using Individual Offender Data in Dutch Neighborhoods conditionally accepted in RESTAT Just heard that my paper Social Interactions and Crime Revisited: An Investigation Using Individual Offender Data in Dutch Neighborhoods written together with Wim Bernasco, Jan Rouwendal and Wouter Steenbeek is conditionally accepted in the Review of Economics and Statistics. Im am rather happy with this result; especially given the fact that we have worked on this for more than 5 years (not consecutively but still).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stedelijke voorzieningen en bevolking: wie woont waar en waarom?</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/2014-02-15-soortzoektsoort/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/2014-02-15-soortzoektsoort/</guid>
      <description>Waarom zijn sommige steden aantrekkelijker dan andere steden? Eén van de belangrijke en boeiende onderzoeksvragen in de ruimtelijke economie betreft het verklaren waarom sommige steden aantrekkelijker zijn voor huishoudens en bedrijven dan andere. Als maatstaven voor aantrekkelijkheid worden vaak lonen en huizenprijzen genomen en deze verschillen inderdaad significant tussen gemeenten in Nederland. Zoals bijvoorbeeld de publicatie Stad en Land (De Groot e.a., 2010) al liet zien, kunnen de verschillen tussen grondprijzen in Nederland oplopen tot een factor 200 per vierkante meter kunnen jaarlonen verschillen tot 7 procent voor een zelfde soort baan.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>