<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>research | Thomas de Graaff</title>
    <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/categories/research/</link>
      <atom:link href="thomasdegraaff.nl/categories/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>research</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Thomas de Graaff, 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>research</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/categories/research/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Does new information technology change commuting behavior?</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/post/2019-01-10-informationtechnology/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/post/2019-01-10-informationtechnology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our paper &lt;em&gt;Does new information technology change commuting behavior&lt;/em&gt;
written together with Sergejs Gubins and Jos van Ommeren is accepted
in the &lt;strong&gt;Annals of Regional Science&lt;/strong&gt;. It turned out to be nice paper
with an interesting main message: commuting in total did not change
under the advent of ICT. Our identification is interesting, albeit that
it hinges upon a very strong idenfitication assumption. Apart from ICT
trend in change of commuting do not differ amongst sector-job combinations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those interested: until February 3, 2019, free e-Offprints (as PDF file)
can be downloaded from 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.springer.com/home?SGWID=0-0-1003-0-0&amp;amp;aqId=3665034&amp;amp;download=1&amp;amp;checkval=5cd251c6bd709f5347a4be80748ab3ba&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The abstract reads as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We estimate the long-run causal effect of information technology,
i.e., Internet and powerful computers, as measured by the adoption of
teleworking, on average commuting distance within professions in the
Netherlands. We employ data for 2 years, 1996 when information
technology was hardly adopted and 2010 when information technology
was widely used in a wide range of professions. Variation in
information technology adoption over time and between professions
allows us to infer the causal effect of interest using
difference-in-differences techniques combined with propensity score
matching. Our results show that the long-run causal effect of
information technology on commuting distance is too small to be
identified and likely to be absent. This suggests that, contrary to
some assertions, the advent of information technology did not have a
profound impact on the spatial structure of the labor market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Valuation of Ethnic Diversity: Heterogeneous Effects in an Integrated Labor and Housing Market</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/post/2018-11-18-valuationofethnicdiversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/post/2018-11-18-valuationofethnicdiversity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our paper &lt;em&gt;Valuation of Ethnic Diversity: Heterogeneous Effects in an Integrated Labor and Housing Market&lt;/em&gt; written together with Jessie Bakens is accepted in the &lt;strong&gt;Journal of Economic Geopraphy&lt;/strong&gt;. Jessie and I worked quite hard on this and I am glad that we got the results. The abstract reads as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;We estimate the heterogeneous impact of the scale, composition and consumer good-effect of ethnic diversity on individuals&#39; job and residential location. Using an extensive pooled micro panel-data set in which homeowners in the Netherlands are identified in both the housing and labor market we can derive the combined effect of ethnic diversity in both markets. We test a model that integrates the utility and production function such that the location of work and residence are determined simultaneously by taking into account observed and unobserved heterogeneous individual behavior on both markets. We find that the scale of ethnic diversity, i.e., the share of immigrants, at the city level is mostly positively related to both wages and house prices. This is mainly through a positive productivity effect of immigrants, which results in negative implicit prices for housing (although small) in a city with a higher scale of ethnic diversity for the majority of the individuals in our data. The scale of ethnic diversity is only positively related to utility for a small group of homeowners, while the composition (diversity among immigrants) and consumer good-effect (ethnic diversity of restaurants) of ethnic diversity show overall no significant effect on both markets nor significant implicit prices. Moreover, we find that the majority of Dutch homeowners do not sort themselves out over municipalities by their preferences for ethnic diversity.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Barriers of Culture, Networks, and Language</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/post/2018-05-01-barriersofculturenetworksandlanguage/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/post/2018-05-01-barriersofculturenetworksandlanguage/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A new pubication is out in &lt;em&gt;REGION&lt;/em&gt; with Zhiling Wang and Peter
Nijkamp titled &lt;strong&gt;Barriers of Culture, Networks, and Language&lt;/strong&gt;. A
direct link can be found

&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.18335/region.v5i1.203&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
, with the following
abstract:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along with the increasing pace of globalization, recent decades faced
a dramatically increase in international migrant flows as
well. Compared to the flows of trade, capital and knowledge, we
observe that contemporaneous complex institutional differences,
historical backgrounds, and individuals&amp;rsquo; diverse socio-demographic
characteristics make the migrant workers&amp;rsquo; choice of destination
arguably much more uncontrollable. This study shows that migration is
in a complex way intertwined with culture, networks and language, (i)
by reviewing related studies on the barriers of culture, networks and
language in international labor mobility, and (ii) by exploring
missing gaps and prospective avenues for research. Nowadays, the
migration pressure on Europe and the United states has created
substantial challenges, leading to an urgent need to address the
economic assimilation and social integration of migrants. Against
this background, we emphasize that these non-economic factors have
played an increasingly critical role in shaping international
migration and its future socio-economic consequences for destination
countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Heatmap of the Robustness of Determinants of European City growth</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/post/a-heatmap-of-the-robustness-of-determinants-of-european-city-growth/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/post/a-heatmap-of-the-robustness-of-determinants-of-european-city-growth/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding what makes a city tick (e.g., the determinants that makes cities succesful in employment of economic growth) is vital for both policy makers and (regional) economists. Indeed, local policy makers usually want to know what they can contribute to the performance of their city or region. If policy makers can at all influence the performance, then most likely instruments vary between cities and regions. What is good for one city is not necessarily good for another. To analyse this, I ran many regressions of combinations of determinants and analyse their robustness (e.g., sign changes, changes in significance level and coefficients). The research is commissioned by the PBL Netherlands Environmental Assessment Agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-problem&#34;&gt;The problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way of looking at city or regional performance is to make use of growth models. Typically, an empirical growth model comes in the following shape:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$
\ln(\frac{y_t}{y_0})=\ln(y_0)+\mathbf{X}\beta+\epsilon,
$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where $y_t$ denotes a regional or city performance measure (gdp or employment), so $\ln(\frac{y_t}{y_0})$ denotes the growth rate of $y$ between $t$ and $0$. On the right hand side, typically one controls for the initial state of $y$ at time $0$ and for a whole bunch of other variables $\mathbf{X}$. And it is exactly these variables we are interested in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which variables, if any, have a systematic and robust impact on the growth rate of $y$?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we estimate the model above multiple times where each time $\mathbf{X}$ is formed by a subset of all determinants (in our case we use for each regression 4 variables out of around 70). This yield a database of many regression results (actually two databased: one with the coefficients and one with the t-values). One way of assessing the robustness of a particular indicator is to look at how many times that indicator is signicant and display the percentage in a heatmap&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;creating-a-heat-map-of-the-regression-results&#34;&gt;Creating a heat map of the regression results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After I have run all possible regressions (and there are many given the formula $\frac{71!}{4!(71-4)!}$, I can perform an ex-post analysis on the results. For my purpose, I have looked at city gdp for all sectors combined, and separately for 7 sectors and have created a dataset that consists of how many times (in percentages) a variable was significant in the regression above. This had led to the table below with sectors as variables and each determinant as an observation (alas, sector names and variables are in Dutch).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt; data
# A tibble: 71 × 8
                      Variable    Totaal     Landbouw Constructie         fbs   Industrie
                         &amp;lt;chr&amp;gt;     &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;        &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;       &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;       &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;       &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;
1                        Banen 0.9999791 0.6722262812 0.999937376 0.846926208 1.000000000
2            Levensverwachting 1.0000000 0.9523640539 0.999519883 0.816386598 0.845819852
3          Kwaliteit onderwijs 0.9756184 0.0577601503 0.694269909 0.998893644 0.579000104
4                    Recreatie 0.5286922 0.0000000000 0.999874752 0.595031834 0.593695856
5                 Natuurrampen 1.0000000 0.0002087465 0.082580106 0.985867863 0.006137146
6            Clustering chemie 0.8412901 0.0003131197 0.027157917 0.291034339 0.034631041
7       Specialisatie landbouw 0.9799395 0.0001878718 0.225634067 1.000000000 0.045360610
8  Specialisatie electriciteit 0.9998956 0.0001669972 0.005531782 0.004905542 0.999645131
9               Bereikbaarheid 0.9505062 0.2850224402 0.759482309 0.999979125 0.935392965
10                     Cultuur 0.9457468 0.0352364054 1.000000000 0.973363949 0.828368646
# ... with 61 more rows, and 2 more variables: `Niet markt diensten` &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;, wrtdchc &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make a heat map I first have to create a tidy dataset using the gather function:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt; data &amp;lt;- gather(data, sector, waarde, -Variable)
&amp;gt; data
# A tibble: 497 × 3
                      Variable sector    waarde
                         &amp;lt;chr&amp;gt;  &amp;lt;chr&amp;gt;     &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;
1                        Banen Totaal 0.9999791
2            Levensverwachting Totaal 1.0000000
3          Kwaliteit onderwijs Totaal 0.9756184
4                    Recreatie Totaal 0.5286922
5                 Natuurrampen Totaal 1.0000000
6            Clustering chemie Totaal 0.8412901
7       Specialisatie landbouw Totaal 0.9799395
8  Specialisatie electriciteit Totaal 0.9998956
9               Bereikbaarheid Totaal 0.9505062
10                     Cultuur Totaal 0.9457468
# ... with 487 more rows
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be able to sort the heat map based on average values, I create a new variable with the average of all the percentages, order it in descending order and refactor the sector names, so that it remains in the order I want in the heatmap:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;data &amp;lt;- data %&amp;gt;%
  group_by(Variable) %&amp;gt;%
  mutate(gemiddelde  = mean(waarde), 
    sector &amp;lt;- as.character(sector),
    sector &amp;lt;- factor(sector, 
              levels=c(&amp;quot;Totaal&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Landbouw&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Constructie&amp;quot;, 
                       &amp;quot;fbs&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Industrie&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Niet markt diensten&amp;quot;,
                       &amp;quot;wrtdchc&amp;quot;))) %&amp;gt;%
  arrange(desc(gemiddelde))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data now looks like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt; data
# A tibble: 497 × 6
            Variable              sector    waarde gemiddelde `sector &amp;lt;- as.character(sector)`
               &amp;lt;chr&amp;gt;              &amp;lt;fctr&amp;gt;     &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;      &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;                            &amp;lt;chr&amp;gt;
1     Waarde in 1991              Totaal 1.0000000  1.0000000                           Totaal
2     Waarde in 1991            Landbouw 1.0000000  1.0000000                         Landbouw
3     Waarde in 1991         Constructie 1.0000000  1.0000000                      Constructie
4     Waarde in 1991                 fbs 1.0000000  1.0000000                              fbs
5     Waarde in 1991           Industrie 1.0000000  1.0000000                        Industrie
6     Waarde in 1991 Niet markt diensten 1.0000000  1.0000000              Niet markt diensten
7     Waarde in 1991             wrtdchc 1.0000000  1.0000000                          wrtdchc
8  Levensverwachting              Totaal 1.0000000  0.9134179                           Totaal
9  Levensverwachting            Landbouw 0.9523641  0.9134179                         Landbouw
10 Levensverwachting         Constructie 0.9995199  0.9134179                      Constructie
# ... with 487 more rows, and 1 more variables: `sector &amp;lt;- factor(sector, levels =
#   c(&amp;quot;...` &amp;lt;fctr&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the &lt;code&gt;geom_tile&lt;/code&gt; aesthetic from &lt;code&gt;ggplot2&lt;/code&gt; I can now create the heat map I want as follows (note that I used the package &lt;code&gt;RColorBrewer&lt;/code&gt; for my colour palette):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  # Note that for ggplot I still have to reorder the variable I want based on the gemiddelde
  p &amp;lt;- ggplot(data,aes(x = sector, y = reorder(Variable,gemiddelde))) +  
     geom_tile(aes(fill = waarde),colour = &amp;quot;white&amp;quot;) + 
     scale_fill_distiller(&amp;quot;Percentage\nsignificant&amp;quot;, 
                          palette = &amp;quot;Spectral&amp;quot;) +
     theme_grey(base_size = 9) + 
     labs(x = &amp;quot;&amp;quot;,y = &amp;quot;&amp;quot;) + 
     scale_x_discrete(expand = c(0, 0)) +
       scale_y_discrete(expand = c(0, 0)) + 
       theme(axis.ticks = element_blank(), 
        axis.text.x = element_text(size = 9 *0.8, 
        angle = 330, hjust = 0, colour = &amp;quot;grey50&amp;quot;))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which finally produces the following plot.&lt;/p&gt;















&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;thomasdegraaff.nl/img/heatmap_gva.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Heatmap of percentage significance of indicators on European city growth.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;thomasdegraaff.nl/img/heatmap_gva.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Heatmap of percentage significance of indicators on European city growth.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;implications&#34;&gt;Implications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When looking at the plot above, it is remarkable that most of the variables are not significant at all times. Worse, most of them are not even significant 75% or even 50% of all cases. This casts great doubt upon the robustness and even validity of most of the determinants oftentimes used in these type of analyses. On the other hand, some of the determinants of city growth may only be important in combination with other determinants. So the next step, would be to look at the impact conditional on other determinants.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stedelijke voorzieningen en bevolking: wie woont waar en waarom?</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/post/2014-02-15-soortzoektsoort/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/post/2014-02-15-soortzoektsoort/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;waarom-zijn-sommige-steden-aantrekkelijker-dan-andere-steden&#34;&gt;Waarom zijn sommige steden aantrekkelijker dan andere steden?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eén van de belangrijke en boeiende onderzoeksvragen in de ruimtelijke economie betreft het verklaren waarom sommige steden aantrekkelijker zijn voor huishoudens en bedrijven dan andere. Als maatstaven voor aantrekkelijkheid worden vaak lonen en huizenprijzen genomen en deze verschillen inderdaad significant tussen gemeenten in Nederland. Zoals bijvoorbeeld de publicatie Stad en Land (De Groot e.a., 2010) al liet zien, kunnen de verschillen tussen grondprijzen in Nederland oplopen tot een factor 200 per vierkante meter kunnen jaarlonen verschillen tot 7 procent voor een zelfde soort baan. Een belangrijke verklaring voor deze verschillen ligt in de aanwezigheid van (stedelijke) voorzieningen. Huishoudens kunnen nu eenmaal een voorkeur hebben voor een historische binnenstad, de aanwezigheid van veel horeca of veel groenvoorzieningen en zijn daarom bereid om een relatief hogere huizenprijs te betalen; het is dus de locatie die voor een deel de huizenprijs bepaalt. Evenzo kunnen voorzieningen ertoe leiden dat werkgevers een voorkeur hebben voor een bepaald vestigingsgebied, en in het uiterste geval kunnen er zelfs productiviteitsverschillen ontstaan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deze publicatie geeft inzicht in de heterogene verschillen en kan 
&lt;a href=&#34;thomasdegraaff.nl/papers/StedelijkeVoorzieningen.pdf&#34;&gt;hier&lt;/a&gt;
 gedownload worden.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
