<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Thomas on Thomas de Graaff</title>
    <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Thomas on Thomas de Graaff</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Does new information technology change commuting behavior?</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/2019-01-10-informationtechnology/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/2019-01-10-informationtechnology/</guid>
      <description>Our paper Does new information technology change commuting behavior written together with Sergejs Gubins and Jos van Ommeren is accepted in the Annals of Regional Science. It turned out to be nice paper with an interesting main message: commuting in total did not change under the advent of ICT. Our identification is interesting, albeit that it hinges upon a very strong idenfitication assumption. Apart from ICT trend in change of commuting do not differ amongst sector-job combinations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Valuation of Ethnic Diversity: Heterogeneous Effects in an Integrated Labor and Housing Market</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/2018-11-18-valuationofethnicdiversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/2018-11-18-valuationofethnicdiversity/</guid>
      <description>Our paper Valuation of Ethnic Diversity: Heterogeneous Effects in an Integrated Labor and Housing Market written together with Jessie Bakens is accepted in the Journal of Economic Geopraphy. Jessie and I worked quite hard on this and I am glad that we got the results. The abstract reads as follows:
&amp;gt;We estimate the heterogeneous impact of the scale, composition and consumer good-effect of ethnic diversity on individuals&#39; job and residential location.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Barriers of Culture, Networks, and Language</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/2018-05-01-barriersofculturenetworksandlanguage/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/2018-05-01-barriersofculturenetworksandlanguage/</guid>
      <description>A new pubication is out in REGION with Zhiling Wang and Peter Nijkamp titled Barriers of Culture, Networks, and Language. A direct link can be found here, with the following abstract:
Abstract  Along with the increasing pace of globalization, recent decades faced a dramatically increase in international migrant flows as well. Compared to the flows of trade, capital and knowledge, we observe that contemporaneous complex institutional differences, historical backgrounds, and individuals&amp;rsquo; diverse socio-demographic characteristics make the migrant workers&amp;rsquo; choice of destination arguably much more uncontrollable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Economic Geography model with R</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/new-economic-geography-model-with-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/new-economic-geography-model-with-r/</guid>
      <description>New economic geography model with R Introduction Why some regions have more economic activiy than others depend on a variety of factors, including regions&amp;rsquo; endowments, good policy and just sheer luck (oftentimes called path dependency). In the 1990s Paul Krugman constructed a model, the Core-Periphery model, that was able to model all these three elements. This model received quite some positive criticism (including a Nobel price), but still is rather complex in wielding it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Migrating from Jekyll to Hugo</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/2017-12-22-migrating/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Dec 2017 14:08:26 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/2017-12-22-migrating/</guid>
      <description>Introduction For quite some time I have been thinking about migrating my (very small) website to the Hugo platform. Mostly because I admire the information rich structure of Kieran Healy&#39;s website and he converted already from Jekyll to Hugo a while ago. Because my website is indeed quite small, it does not suffer from Jekyll oftentimes being slow. However, I needed some additional features of my Jekyll site (e.g., converting bibtex to a reference list), which could not automatically be rendered by Github which is my choice of deployment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sortingmod: an R-package for sorting models</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/sortingmod-an-r-package-for-sorting-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/sortingmod-an-r-package-for-sorting-models/</guid>
      <description>Overview sortingmod is a package for estimating the sorting model - a discrete choice model which explains the location decision of heterogeneous individuals over a set of alternative locations. The model is developed by Bayer et al. (2004) following the work of Berry et al. (1995). It relies on the assumptions that individuals choose a location that maximizes their utility, and that heterogeneous individuals with different characteristics have different preferences, and different valuation for location characteristics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Choosing statistical software packages for education in the social sciences</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/choosing-statistical-software-package-for-education-in-the-social-sciences/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/choosing-statistical-software-package-for-education-in-the-social-sciences/</guid>
      <description>Introduction: the empirical workflow  Econometrics is much easier without the data&amp;mdash;Marno Verbeek
 The quote above does not only apply to economics and econometrics, but to all of the social sciences in general. Empirical research&amp;mdash;that is, dealing with data in all its forms&amp;mdash;requires a rigorous approach, even more so, with the increasing emphasis on openness and reproducibility of all kinds of scientific research. Therefore, it is strange that in academic education there is not much guidance in choosing which research tools to use and in the philosophy behing choosing an efficient and reproducable workflow.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A lines map of building height in Amsterdam</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/a-lines-map-of-building-height-in-amsterdam/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/a-lines-map-of-building-height-in-amsterdam/</guid>
      <description>Introduction I just came across this wonderfull post on https://www.r-bloggers.com http://spatial.ly/2017/04/population-lines-how-and-why-i-created-it/ called Population Lines: How and Why I Created it) by James Cheshire. It allows for wonderfull (and artistic) maps constructed by only varations in height of horizontal lines. One might wonder how useful they are, but they sure are beautiful as one can see below in the population lines map of Europe.
  Population lines map of Europe (source http://blog.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Heatmap of the Robustness of Determinants of European City growth</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/a-heatmap-of-the-robustness-of-determinants-of-european-city-growth/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/a-heatmap-of-the-robustness-of-determinants-of-european-city-growth/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Understanding what makes a city tick (e.g., the determinants that makes cities succesful in employment of economic growth) is vital for both policy makers and (regional) economists. Indeed, local policy makers usually want to know what they can contribute to the performance of their city or region. If policy makers can at all influence the performance, then most likely instruments vary between cities and regions. What is good for one city is not necessarily good for another.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social Interaction and Crime</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/2016-09-12-socialinteractionandcrime/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/2016-09-12-socialinteractionandcrime/</guid>
      <description>Social Interaction and Crime: An Investigation Using Individual Offender Data in Dutch Neighborhoods conditionally accepted in RESTAT Just heard that my paper Social Interactions and Crime Revisited: An Investigation Using Individual Offender Data in Dutch Neighborhoods written together with Wim Bernasco, Jan Rouwendal and Wouter Steenbeek is conditionally accepted in the Review of Economics and Statistics. Im am rather happy with this result; especially given the fact that we have worked on this for more than 5 years (not consecutively but still).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Promotion Zhiling Wang</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/2016-09-06-promotionzhilingwang/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/2016-09-06-promotionzhilingwang/</guid>
      <description>Promotion and defense ceremony of Zhiling Wang My second Ph.D. student got her Ph.D. degree! With an almost flawless defense and a very good Ph.D. thesis Zhiling obviously deserves all the credit. However, I could not resist to post this picture. Somehow, I resemble Jose Mourinho, the angry looking football trainer.
  At the promotion of Zhiling Wang   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drawing Edgeworth boxes with LaTeX</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/2015-11-25-edgeworth/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/2015-11-25-edgeworth/</guid>
      <description>Factor mobility and welfare For educational purposes we teach in the second year&#39;s course regional and urban economics students the Edgeworth-Bowley box. At first sight the concept is quite simple, but because there are restrictions for the total amount of both labour and capital in both regions or countries, the intuition behind the model and especially the drawing of the box is rather complex. Therefore, I once wrote a straightforward but elaborate LaTeX script invoking the Tikz package.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Krugman&#39;s Increasing Returns and Economic Geography</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/2015-10-05-krugman/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/2015-10-05-krugman/</guid>
      <description>Drawing the diagram of a stylized version of Krugman&#39;s Increasing Returns and Economic Geography For educational purposes we teach in the second year&#39;s course regional and urban economics a simplified version of Krugman&#39;s model in his paper titled Increasing Returns and Economic Geography. The model we have adopted goes as follows:
We consider a simplified economy with two regions and 1 (million) workers ( $L=1$ ) in total. Region 1 is inhabited by 100,000 farmers (bound to their land so immobile), while in Region 2 there are 200,000 farmers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cultural diversity versus cultural distance</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/2015-07-29-culturaldiversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/2015-07-29-culturaldiversity/</guid>
      <description>With Zhiling Wang and Peter Nijkamp
 This study analyses the impact of cultural composition on regional attractiveness from the perspective of international migrant sorting behavior on a European regional NUTS1 level. We use an attitudinal survey to quantify cultural distances between natives and immigrants in the region concerned, and estimate the migrants’ varying preferences for both cultural diversity and cultural distance. To account for regional unobserved heterogeneity, our econometric analysis employs artificial instrumental variables, as developed by Bayer et al.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>WooW-II: Workshop on open Workflows</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/2015-07-29-woow-ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/2015-07-29-woow-ii/</guid>
      <description>With Daniel Arribas-Bel
This resource describes WooW-II, a two-day workshop on open workflows for quantitative social scientists. The workshop is broken down in five main parts, where each of them typically consists of an introductionary tutorial and a hands-on assignment. The specific tools discussed in this workshop are Markdown, Pandoc, Git, Github, R, and Rstudio, but the theoretical approach applies to a wider range of tools (e.g., LaTeX, and Python).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stedelijke voorzieningen en bevolking: wie woont waar en waarom?</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/2014-02-15-soortzoektsoort/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/2014-02-15-soortzoektsoort/</guid>
      <description>Waarom zijn sommige steden aantrekkelijker dan andere steden? Eén van de belangrijke en boeiende onderzoeksvragen in de ruimtelijke economie betreft het verklaren waarom sommige steden aantrekkelijker zijn voor huishoudens en bedrijven dan andere. Als maatstaven voor aantrekkelijkheid worden vaak lonen en huizenprijzen genomen en deze verschillen inderdaad significant tussen gemeenten in Nederland. Zoals bijvoorbeeld de publicatie Stad en Land (De Groot e.a., 2010) al liet zien, kunnen de verschillen tussen grondprijzen in Nederland oplopen tot een factor 200 per vierkante meter kunnen jaarlonen verschillen tot 7 procent voor een zelfde soort baan.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>