<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>publication | Thomas de Graaff</title>
    <link>https://www.thomasdegraaff.nl/categories/publication/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://www.thomasdegraaff.nl/categories/publication/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>publication</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Thomas de Graaff, 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>publication</title>
      <link>https://www.thomasdegraaff.nl/categories/publication/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Does new information technology change commuting behavior?</title>
      <link>https://www.thomasdegraaff.nl/post/2019-01-10-informationtechnology/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.thomasdegraaff.nl/post/2019-01-10-informationtechnology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our paper &lt;em&gt;Does new information technology change commuting behavior&lt;/em&gt;
written together with Sergejs Gubins and Jos van Ommeren is accepted
in the &lt;strong&gt;Annals of Regional Science&lt;/strong&gt;. It turned out to be nice paper
with an interesting main message: commuting in total did not change
under the advent of ICT. Our identification is interesting, albeit that
it hinges upon a very strong idenfitication assumption. Apart from ICT
trend in change of commuting do not differ amongst sector-job combinations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those interested: until February 3, 2019, free e-Offprints (as PDF file)
can be downloaded from 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.springer.com/home?SGWID=0-0-1003-0-0&amp;amp;aqId=3665034&amp;amp;download=1&amp;amp;checkval=5cd251c6bd709f5347a4be80748ab3ba&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The abstract reads as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We estimate the long-run causal effect of information technology,
i.e., Internet and powerful computers, as measured by the adoption of
teleworking, on average commuting distance within professions in the
Netherlands. We employ data for 2 years, 1996 when information
technology was hardly adopted and 2010 when information technology
was widely used in a wide range of professions. Variation in
information technology adoption over time and between professions
allows us to infer the causal effect of interest using
difference-in-differences techniques combined with propensity score
matching. Our results show that the long-run causal effect of
information technology on commuting distance is too small to be
identified and likely to be absent. This suggests that, contrary to
some assertions, the advent of information technology did not have a
profound impact on the spatial structure of the labor market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Valuation of Ethnic Diversity: Heterogeneous Effects in an Integrated Labor and Housing Market</title>
      <link>https://www.thomasdegraaff.nl/post/2018-11-18-valuationofethnicdiversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.thomasdegraaff.nl/post/2018-11-18-valuationofethnicdiversity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our paper &lt;em&gt;Valuation of Ethnic Diversity: Heterogeneous Effects in an Integrated Labor and Housing Market&lt;/em&gt; written together with Jessie Bakens is accepted in the &lt;strong&gt;Journal of Economic Geopraphy&lt;/strong&gt;. Jessie and I worked quite hard on this and I am glad that we got the results. The abstract reads as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;We estimate the heterogeneous impact of the scale, composition and consumer good-effect of ethnic diversity on individuals&#39; job and residential location. Using an extensive pooled micro panel-data set in which homeowners in the Netherlands are identified in both the housing and labor market we can derive the combined effect of ethnic diversity in both markets. We test a model that integrates the utility and production function such that the location of work and residence are determined simultaneously by taking into account observed and unobserved heterogeneous individual behavior on both markets. We find that the scale of ethnic diversity, i.e., the share of immigrants, at the city level is mostly positively related to both wages and house prices. This is mainly through a positive productivity effect of immigrants, which results in negative implicit prices for housing (although small) in a city with a higher scale of ethnic diversity for the majority of the individuals in our data. The scale of ethnic diversity is only positively related to utility for a small group of homeowners, while the composition (diversity among immigrants) and consumer good-effect (ethnic diversity of restaurants) of ethnic diversity show overall no significant effect on both markets nor significant implicit prices. Moreover, we find that the majority of Dutch homeowners do not sort themselves out over municipalities by their preferences for ethnic diversity.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Barriers of Culture, Networks, and Language</title>
      <link>https://www.thomasdegraaff.nl/post/2018-05-01-barriersofculturenetworksandlanguage/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.thomasdegraaff.nl/post/2018-05-01-barriersofculturenetworksandlanguage/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A new pubication is out in &lt;em&gt;REGION&lt;/em&gt; with Zhiling Wang and Peter
Nijkamp titled &lt;strong&gt;Barriers of Culture, Networks, and Language&lt;/strong&gt;. A
direct link can be found

&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.18335/region.v5i1.203&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
, with the following
abstract:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along with the increasing pace of globalization, recent decades faced
a dramatically increase in international migrant flows as
well. Compared to the flows of trade, capital and knowledge, we
observe that contemporaneous complex institutional differences,
historical backgrounds, and individuals&amp;rsquo; diverse socio-demographic
characteristics make the migrant workers&amp;rsquo; choice of destination
arguably much more uncontrollable. This study shows that migration is
in a complex way intertwined with culture, networks and language, (i)
by reviewing related studies on the barriers of culture, networks and
language in international labor mobility, and (ii) by exploring
missing gaps and prospective avenues for research. Nowadays, the
migration pressure on Europe and the United states has created
substantial challenges, leading to an urgent need to address the
economic assimilation and social integration of migrants. Against
this background, we emphasize that these non-economic factors have
played an increasingly critical role in shaping international
migration and its future socio-economic consequences for destination
countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cultural diversity versus cultural distance</title>
      <link>https://www.thomasdegraaff.nl/post/2015-07-29-culturaldiversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.thomasdegraaff.nl/post/2015-07-29-culturaldiversity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;With Zhiling Wang and Peter Nijkamp&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study analyses the impact of cultural composition on regional attractiveness from the perspective of international migrant sorting behavior on a European regional NUTS1 level. We use an attitudinal survey to quantify cultural distances between natives and immigrants in the region concerned, and estimate the migrants’ varying preferences for both cultural diversity and cultural distance. To account for regional unobserved heterogeneity, our econometric analysis employs artificial instrumental variables, as developed by Bayer et al. (2004b). The main conclusions are twofold. On the one hand, cultural diversity increases regional attractiveness. On the other hand, average cultural distance greatly weakens regional attractiveness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This basically means that migrants value diversity as long as the cultural distance beteween natives and immigrants is not too large.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a Tinbergen Institute working paper version of this paper (which can be found 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tinbergen.nl/discussionpaper/?paper=2324&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
) and the paper itself is published in &lt;strong&gt;Spatial Economic Analysis&lt;/strong&gt; (for more details see their 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/17421772.2016.1102956#.Vzbx1ZN97Aw&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;
). Note that &lt;strong&gt;Spatial Economic Analysis&lt;/strong&gt; provides an 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tandfonline.com/eprint/VFsNdbTmfnTSHvWkc5PN/full&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;eprint link&lt;/a&gt;
 which gives limited full access to the paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even better than the paper perhaps for some, the journal made as well the funny looking comic below:&lt;/p&gt;















&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://www.thomasdegraaff.nl/img/RSEAculturaldiversity.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Our whole paper in a one-page comic!&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.thomasdegraaff.nl/img/RSEAculturaldiversity.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Our whole paper in a one-page comic!
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stedelijke voorzieningen en bevolking: wie woont waar en waarom?</title>
      <link>https://www.thomasdegraaff.nl/post/2014-02-15-soortzoektsoort/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.thomasdegraaff.nl/post/2014-02-15-soortzoektsoort/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;waarom-zijn-sommige-steden-aantrekkelijker-dan-andere-steden&#34;&gt;Waarom zijn sommige steden aantrekkelijker dan andere steden?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eén van de belangrijke en boeiende onderzoeksvragen in de ruimtelijke economie betreft het verklaren waarom sommige steden aantrekkelijker zijn voor huishoudens en bedrijven dan andere. Als maatstaven voor aantrekkelijkheid worden vaak lonen en huizenprijzen genomen en deze verschillen inderdaad significant tussen gemeenten in Nederland. Zoals bijvoorbeeld de publicatie Stad en Land (De Groot e.a., 2010) al liet zien, kunnen de verschillen tussen grondprijzen in Nederland oplopen tot een factor 200 per vierkante meter kunnen jaarlonen verschillen tot 7 procent voor een zelfde soort baan. Een belangrijke verklaring voor deze verschillen ligt in de aanwezigheid van (stedelijke) voorzieningen. Huishoudens kunnen nu eenmaal een voorkeur hebben voor een historische binnenstad, de aanwezigheid van veel horeca of veel groenvoorzieningen en zijn daarom bereid om een relatief hogere huizenprijs te betalen; het is dus de locatie die voor een deel de huizenprijs bepaalt. Evenzo kunnen voorzieningen ertoe leiden dat werkgevers een voorkeur hebben voor een bepaald vestigingsgebied, en in het uiterste geval kunnen er zelfs productiviteitsverschillen ontstaan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deze publicatie geeft inzicht in de heterogene verschillen en kan 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thomasdegraaff.nl/papers/StedelijkeVoorzieningen.pdf&#34;&gt;hier&lt;/a&gt;
 gedownload worden.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
