<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Reproducability on Thomas de Graaff</title>
    <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/categories/reproducability/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Reproducability on Thomas de Graaff</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="thomasdegraaff.nl/categories/reproducability/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Sortingmod: an R-package for sorting models</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/sortingmod-an-r-package-for-sorting-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/sortingmod-an-r-package-for-sorting-models/</guid>
      <description>Overview sortingmod is a package for estimating the sorting model - a discrete choice model which explains the location decision of heterogeneous individuals over a set of alternative locations. The model is developed by Bayer et al. (2004) following the work of Berry et al. (1995). It relies on the assumptions that individuals choose a location that maximizes their utility, and that heterogeneous individuals with different characteristics have different preferences, and different valuation for location characteristics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Choosing statistical software packages for education in the social sciences</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/choosing-statistical-software-package-for-education-in-the-social-sciences/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/choosing-statistical-software-package-for-education-in-the-social-sciences/</guid>
      <description>Introduction: the empirical workflow  Econometrics is much easier without the data&amp;mdash;Marno Verbeek
 The quote above does not only apply to economics and econometrics, but to all of the social sciences in general. Empirical research&amp;mdash;that is, dealing with data in all its forms&amp;mdash;requires a rigorous approach, even more so, with the increasing emphasis on openness and reproducibility of all kinds of scientific research. Therefore, it is strange that in academic education there is not much guidance in choosing which research tools to use and in the philosophy behing choosing an efficient and reproducable workflow.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A lines map of building height in Amsterdam</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/a-lines-map-of-building-height-in-amsterdam/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/a-lines-map-of-building-height-in-amsterdam/</guid>
      <description>Introduction I just came across this wonderfull post on https://www.r-bloggers.com http://spatial.ly/2017/04/population-lines-how-and-why-i-created-it/ called Population Lines: How and Why I Created it) by James Cheshire. It allows for wonderfull (and artistic) maps constructed by only varations in height of horizontal lines. One might wonder how useful they are, but they sure are beautiful as one can see below in the population lines map of Europe.
  Population lines map of Europe (source http://blog.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Heatmap of the Robustness of Determinants of European City growth</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/a-heatmap-of-the-robustness-of-determinants-of-european-city-growth/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/a-heatmap-of-the-robustness-of-determinants-of-european-city-growth/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Understanding what makes a city tick (e.g., the determinants that makes cities succesful in employment of economic growth) is vital for both policy makers and (regional) economists. Indeed, local policy makers usually want to know what they can contribute to the performance of their city or region. If policy makers can at all influence the performance, then most likely instruments vary between cities and regions. What is good for one city is not necessarily good for another.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>WooW-II: Workshop on open Workflows</title>
      <link>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/2015-07-29-woow-ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>thomasdegraaff.nl/thomas/2015-07-29-woow-ii/</guid>
      <description>With Daniel Arribas-Bel
This resource describes WooW-II, a two-day workshop on open workflows for quantitative social scientists. The workshop is broken down in five main parts, where each of them typically consists of an introductionary tutorial and a hands-on assignment. The specific tools discussed in this workshop are Markdown, Pandoc, Git, Github, R, and Rstudio, but the theoretical approach applies to a wider range of tools (e.g., LaTeX, and Python).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>